in this video we're going to talk about
how to calculate the gravitational field
strength generated by the earth
so first
let's draw a picture
so let's say this
is the
earth and
the earth generates its own
gravitational field strength
gravity
causes it's a force that brings matter
together
so let's say if you have an object here
this object will experience
a gravitational force by the earth that
will accelerate it towards the earth
now we want to calculate the
gravitational force i mean the
gravitational field strength at the
center
and first we need a formula
according to newton's second law
the net force acted on an object is
equal to
the mass times the acceleration
when dealing with gravity we need to use
gravitational acceleration which is g
now the gravitational force acting
between two objects let's say the earth
and the moon
these two objects
they fill a force that pulls them
together
that's equal to the gravitational
constant g
times
the masses of the two object
divided by
r squared where r is the distance
between
in this case the center of the earth and
the center of the moon
now we could cancel one of the m values
in this equation
and this will give us
g gravitational acceleration also known
as the gravitational field drift
and that's equal to the gravitational
constant
times the mass of the object
divided by r squared
so that's the formula that we're going
to use
in order to calculate
the gravitational field strength
generated by the earth
now we need to use
the radius of the earth as the r value
so that's going to be the distance from
the center
to the surface of the earth
and that's given to us it's 6380
kilometers
now let's plug in what we know
g the gravitational constant that's 6.67
times 10
to the negative 11
and its newtons
times square meters
over
square kilograms
now let's multiply that by the mass of
the earth which is given to us as well
so that's 5.97
times 10 to the 24
kilograms
and then we're going to divide that by
the radius of the earth
now this is in kilometers but we need to
convert that to meters
so we have 63 80 kilometers
and one kilometer
is equivalent to a thousand meters
so pretty much we got to multiply it by
a thousand
and that gives us six million three
hundred eighty thousand meters
so that's the radius of the earth
approximately
now in scientific notation that's going
to be 6.38
times
10 to the 6 meters
you simply need to move the decimal
point
6 units to the left
now
this is r squared so you don't want to
forget to
square that value
now let's go ahead and plug this in
so the answer that i got in this example
is
9.78
and the units
we could cancel a kilogram so there's
one left over because this is squared
we could cancel square meters
so the units is going to be newtons
per kilogram
now this answers for the most part
fairly accurate because we know that the
gravitational acceleration on the earth
is 9.81 meters per second squared and
this rounds close to 9.8
now if we were to use more exact values
we would definitely get an answer close
to this one
so that's how you can calculate the
gravitational field strength generated
at the earth's surface
now let's move on
to
part b
of this problem
how can we calculate the gravitational
field strength
5000 kilometers above the earth's
surface
so our r value is going to change
so this is still the radius of the earth
but we want to find the gravitational
field strength let's say at this point
which we'll call point a
and that's
5 000 kilometers above the surface of
the earth
and the radius of the earth is 63
80 kilometers
so
the r value that we need to plug in
to this equation it's going to be the
sum
of those two values
so 6380 plus 5000
that's 11
388 kilometers
if we multiply that by a thousand
that's going to be
11 million
000 meters
and in scientific notation
if we move the decimal one two three
four
five six seven spaces to the left
this is going to be 1.138
times 10 to the 7 meters
so that's the only thing that's
different in this problem
just the r value
so what you need to know is that as r
increases as you move away from the
surface of the earth
the gravitational field decreases
and notice that r is squared
if you double the distance the
gravitational field strength reduces by
a factor four
if r were to increase by a factor of
three the gravitational field strength
would decrease
by a factor of nine it would be three
squared
and so gravity
the gravitational field strength greatly
weakens
with increase in distance so the further
that you move away from the earth
the weaker
the force of gravity that the earth will
exert on you
now let's plug in the numbers into this
equation
so g is going to be the same
we don't need to put the units in
because we know what the units for the
final answer will be
the mass of the earth is still going to
be the same 5.97
times 10 to the 24
kilograms
and now we're going to plug in
our new
r value
so it's 1.138
times 10 to the 7 meters
so you want to make sure that you
convert kilometers to meters in order to
get this question right and second don't
forget to square this value
so the answer that i got
in this problem
is
3.07
meters per second squared
so as you can see
the gravitational field strength
greatly weakens as you move away from a
planet
now let's use another example to
illustrate this
so let's say we have planet x
and at a distance
from the center of x to some point
a
let's say that distance is 5 000
kilometers
you know the gravitational field
strength
is
let's say
newtons per kilogram
given that information
what will be
the gravitational field strength at
point b
if it's at
10 000
kilometers away from the center
now in this case
we know the formula but we really don't
have to plug in
any values
we don't even need to know the mass of
the planet to get the answer all we need
to understand is the relationship
between g
and r squared that g
is inversely related to the square of
the distance
so notice that the distance increased by
a factor of two it went from five
thousand to ten thousand
so if r goes up by a factor of two
what's going to happen to the
gravitational field strength
one over two squared is one over four so
it's going to be four times less it's
going to decrease
by a factor of four
so if we take 40 and divide it by four
then we know that the gravitational
field strength at point b
will be 10
newtons per kilogram
and so that's how you can calculate the
gravitational field strength at some
distance if you don't know the mass of
the planet
if you know the
gravitational distance at point a and
you know how far you are from the center
of the planet
then you could use that to calculate the
gravitational field strength at point b